We have seen a few examples of concatenating text
so far in this course, but we often want more
control over how text is displayed, especially
if we are trying to display a custom message,
such as giving a game player details on how a
game is going. Take a look at the 322-format file,
which stores values in three variables on
lines 1 through 3, and then prints out a
concatenated string that includes the three
variables on line 5. I will run this code,
and we get a basic message about a player, score,
and level achieved. There are ways in which we
can display this information more smoothly. One
method is to use the string.format method. This
method allows one to control the text spacing
in one statement using whatever variables should
be in the statement. On line 6, I will rewrite
this print statement, using blank sets of curly
brackets for variable placeholders, and then at
the end of the quote, adding dot format and then,
in parentheses, the three variables in the
order I want them displayed: player1, score,
level. I will then run this code, and we see the
sentence as formatted. For a more complex type of
formatting, one could have the variables in the
format function in the same order as defined,
as I will do here, and then go back and fill in
the curly brackets with the index value of each
variable, score being 0, level being 1, and
player1 being 2, as we have seen in lists.
I will place the numbers into the curly brackets
accordingly, I will run the code, and the sentence
prints as expected. The dot format method works
well, but starting in Python 3.6, f-strings have
become a preferred way of formatting strings,
much like template literals in recent iterations
of JavaScript and string interpolation features
in other languages. These features allow you to
embed expressions or variables directly within a
string, making it easier to concatenate and format
text. I will type an f-string print statement
on line 7 and then explain the code. Variables
are in curly brackets, and one does not need to
use an extra function on the end of this code,
saving time in typing and allowing one to focus
more on the presentation of a print statement.